Zafeiria (Iro) Moumoulidou

College of Information & Computer Sciences
University of Massachusetts
140 Governors Drive, Amherst, MA, 01003
zmoumoulidou@cs.umass.edu
https://imoumoulidou.github.io/

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the broad area of ethical, equitable, and responsible systems. I focus on issues of diversity, data and algorithmic fairness, while I am particularly fascinated by the areas of Fair & Explainable AI, Machine Learning, and Recommendation Systems.

EDUCATION

University of Massachusetts

Amherst, MA

Ph.D. in Computer Science, GPA: 3.97/4.00

September 2018-Present

Advisor: Prof. Alexandra Meliou

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF CRETE

Chania, Greece

Diploma (5-year degree) in Electrical & Computer Engineering, GPA: 8.52/10.00 August 2018

Thesis: "Dynamic Decision Trees in a Distributed Environment" Advisors: Prof. Minos Garofalakis, Prof. Antonios Deligiannakis

RESEARCH & ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

University of Massachusetts

Amherst, MA

Research Assistant

Fall 2018-Present

Research on data diversification and algorithmic fairness using techniques from theoretical computer science.

Megagon Labs

Mountain View, CA

Research Scientist Intern

June 2021-August 2021

Research on understanding semantics in structured datasets.

University of Massachusetts

Amherst, MA

Teaching Assistant

Fall 2021

In Research Methods in Empirical Computer Science with Prof. David Jensen.

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Z. Moumoulidou**, A. McGregor, and A. Meliou. Diverse Data Selection under Fairness Constraints. *In 24th International Conference on Database Theory (ICDT 2021)*
- [2] R. Addanki, A. McGregor, A. Meliou, and **Z. Moumoulidou**. Diversity Maximization under Fairness Constraints in Streaming and Distributed Environments.* (under submission)
- * Authors appear in alphabetical order.

AWARDS & DISTINCTIONS

- Outstanding Academic Performance Scholarship, Gerondelis Foundation, (Grant \$5,000)
- 2019
- Nominated by UMass CICS to apply for the Microsoft PhD Fellowship, (1/3 nominations) 2020

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, Java, Matlab/GNU Octave, SQL
- Environments & Tools: PyTorch, MapReduce (Hadoop), Apache Storm

Professional Service & Outreach

- External Reviewer: VLDB 2021 (demonstration track), VLDB 2022, SIGMOD 2022
- Volunteer: PhD Applicant Support Program at CICS UMass

Fall 2021

GRADUATE COURSEWORK

• Advanced Topics in Natural Language Processing, with Prof. Brendan O'Connor (audit)	Spring 2021
• Advanced Machine Learning, with Prof. Benjamin Marlin (A)	Fall 2020
• Randomized Algorithms, with Prof. Andrew McGregor (A)	Spring 2020
• Optimization in Computer Science, with Prof. Madalina Fiterau (A)	Spring 2020
• Neural Networks: A Modern Introduction, with Prof. Erik Learned-Miller (A)	Fall 2019
• Research Methods in Empirical Computer Science, with Prof. David Jensen (A)	Fall 2019
• Advanced Algorithms, with Prof. Ramesh Sitaraman (A-)	Spring 2019
• Database Design & Implementation, with Prof. Gerome Miklau (A)	Fall 2018
• Machine Learning, with Prof. Brendan O'Connor (A)	Fall 2018

NOTABLE UNDERGRADUATE COURSEWORK

- Special Topics in Database Systems (10/10) (graduate course)
- Human Computer Interaction (10/10)
- Convex Optimization (9/10)
- Information Theory (10/10)
- Statistical Signal Processing (9/10)
- Probability Theory & Statistics (9.5/10)

LANGUAGES

- Greek: Native
- English: Certificate of Proficiency in English C2, University of Cambridge, University of Michigan
- Spanish: Diploma Superior de Español Como Lengua Extranjera C2, Instituto Cervantes
- German: Goethe-Zertifikat B2, Goethe-Institut